Preliminary Inventory of the Clarence E. Ekstrom papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Clarence E. Ekstrom papers
1943-1962
75086
Ekstrom, Clarence E. (Clarence Eugene), 1902-1986.
1 manuscript box, 26 envelopes, 1 oversize folder, 3 album boxes (4.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Photographs and printed matter, relating to American naval operations in the Pacific Ocean and Mediterranean Sea, during and after World War II.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1975.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
Clarence E. Ekstrom was born in Waupaca, Wisconsin, and graduated from the United States Naval Academy in 1924. In November 1940 Lieutenant Commander Ekstrom was the commanding officer of reconnaissance squadron VCS-9. Ekstrom was awarded the Navy Cross for his actions during the Battle of Leyte Gulf while commanding the escort carrier USS Savo Island in October 1944.
During 1949 and 1950, Ekstrom commanded the aircraft carrier USS Franklin D. Roosevelt. In 1954 he was awarded the William J. Kossler Award for his achievement in the practical application or operation of a vertical flight aircraft that year. Ekstrom later commanded the Sixth Fleet in the Mediterranean Sea.
Vice Admiral Clarence E. Ekstrom served from October 1959 to November 1962 as Commander, Naval Air Force, United States Pacific Fleet. Under his direction, the combat readiness and capabilities of the Naval Air Force units in the U.S. Pacific Fleet increased, providing the United States with an effective tool for preserving peace in several international crises that arose during his tenure. Through his perseverance, a 'level readiness' program was instituted that overcame previous pilot training deficiencies and had a positive effect on aviation safety in the U.S. Pacific Fleet.
Vice Admiral Ekstrom retired in 1962 and settled in Coronado, California. He passed away on 11 January 1986.
Sources:
Citation (copy) presenting the Distinguished Service Medal to Vice Admiral Clarence E. Ekstrom, United States Navy, undated
"Military Times Hall of Valor: Awards for Clarence Eugene Ekstrom". www.militarytimes.com. Accessed 23 March 2012.
Scope and Content of Collection
Collected by Clarence E. Ekstrom these photographs and printed matter relate to American naval operations in the Pacific Ocean and Mediterranean, during and after World War II.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
United States. Navy--Officers.; World War, 1939-1945--Naval operations.
Collection Contents
- Personal file (Box 1)
  - Distinguished Service Medal to Vice Admiral Clarence E. Ekstrom, United States Navy. Citation (copy), undated (Folder 1)
  - Orders Relieving Vice Admiral Clarence E. Ekstrom, USN, Commander Naval Air Force, Pacific Fleet, of All Active Duty Incident to His Retirement, 1962 November 30 (Folder 1)
- Collected material: Speeches and writings (Box 1)
  - (Folder 1)
  - Economics of Defense in the Nuclear Age, by Charles J. Hitch and Roland N. McKean, report by Captain C. R. Calhoum, undated (Folder 1)
  - Organization for War in Modern Times, lecture by Field Marshal Montgomery, Royal United Service Institution, 1955 October 12 (Folder 1)
  - Extract from speech by General George Decker, Vice Chief of Staff, U.S. Army, annual conference of Army Judge Advocates, Charlottesville, Virginia, 1960 September 6 (Folder 1)
  - Some Navigational Lights for Troubled International Waters, address by Hon. James A. Farley, Chairman of the Board, Coca-Cola Export Corporation, Chicago, 1963 March 15 (Folder 1)
  - Address by Admiral George W. Anderson, Jr., Chief of Naval Operations, Awards Luncheon of the Navy League Convention, San Juan, Puerto Rico, 1963 May 3 (Folder 1)
  - Sea-Based Striking Power, presentation by Vice Admiral P. D. Stroop, U.S. Navy Commander Naval Air Force, United States Pacific Fleet to Aviator-Space Writers Symposium on 23 May, 1963, Dallas, Texas (Folder 1)
- Collected material: Office files (Box 1)
  - United States. Navy Dept., Office of the Chief of Naval Operations, Washington, D.C. (Folder 1)
    - CNO Information, 1959 December 18 (Folder 1)
    - Another Reorganization Threatens, 1960 August 26 (Folder 1)
    - Thoughts on Department of Defense Organization, 1960 September 26 (Folder 1)
    - Matter of Current Importance, personal letter to Retired Flag Officers, 1963, April-July (Folder 1)
  - United States, Naval Aviation (Folder 1)
    - United States Naval Aviation, 1910-1960. Prepared at the direction of the Deputy Chief of Naval Operations (AIR) and the Chief of the Bureau of Naval Weapons (Folder 1)
    - Navy Aircraft Contracts, 1911-1936, photo copy, undated (Folder 1)
    - Aviation Log, Curtiss Hydroaeroplane, Navy No. A-1, 1911 July 1 to 1912 October 16 (Folder 1)
  - Air Force Association. (Folder 1)
    - Memorandum from Howard T. Markey, President, undated (Folder 1)
    - 4 (Four) photographs of Japanese war ships. Includes technical characteristics, undated (Folder 1)
- Printed matter (Box 1)
  - USS Kitty Hawk-CVA63: World's First Guided Missile Attack Aircraft Carrier, pamphlet, undated (Folder 1)
  - Alert: Freedom and You: Facts for the Armed Forces, No. 2. This pamphlet was purchased for the Armed Services by the Directorate for Armed Forces Information and Education, Department of Defense, Washington, D.C., undated (Folder 1)
  - Salvo - The Japs Will Hate The 78, Savo Island, commissioning issue, 1944 (Folder 1)
  - USS Franklin D. Roosevelt, F. D. Reporter, published for the crew, by the crew about their shipmates and shiplife, 1949-1950 (Folder 1)
  - (Folder 1)
  - My Trip With the U.S. Navy: Fall Maneuvers, November 1 to 22, 1949, from Norfolk, Virginia to Arctic Circle in the Davis Straight, and Return, by Wm. F. Hubbard, Hugoton, Kansas, 1950 February 5 (Folder 1)
  - Information Bulletin for Armed Forces Personnel Entering Naples, Italy, Comsubcomnelm/Comhedsuppact, Naples, Italy, 1954 June (Folder 1)
  - USS Forrestal, CVA 59, Christening Newport News, Virginia, 1954 December 11 (Folder 1)
  - U.S.S. Forrestal, CVA 59. Commissioning Norfolk Naval Shipyard, 1955 October 1 (Folder 1)
  - USS Ticonderoga, aircraft carrier CVA 14, 1944-1955 (Folder 1)
  - View 1: The War We are In, prepared by Champion Papers of Hamilton, Ohio, 1960 Winter (Folder 1)
  - Defense Strength of Japan, 1961 Winter (Folder 1)
  - The First Navy Aircraft, Curtiss - Navy Model A-1, Then and Now, 1911-1961 (Folder 1)
  - Reorganization of the Department of Defense: Philosophy and Counter-Philosophy, U.S. Naval Institute, Annapolis, Maryland, 1961 (Folder 1)
  - Japan Maritime Self-Defense Force, Overseas Training Cruise, 1961. Training Squadron (Folder 1)
  - Destroyers in the United States Navy, Naval History Division, Washington, D.C., 1962 (Folder 1)
  - Service Information Summary, Douglas Aircraft Company Inc., Aircraft Division, Long Beach, California. Souvenir issue, 50th Anniversary, Naval Aviation, 1911-1961, 1962 January-February. (Folder 1)
  - Navy Speakers' Notes, published by the Chief of Information, 1963 April-August (Folder 1)
  - Chinfo, newsletter, Chief of Information, Navy Department, Washington, D.C., 1964 (Folder 1)
  - Miscellany. Officers and Directors of the Chamber of Commerce of the United States of America, 1960-1961 (Folder 1)
- Oversize materials (Box Map case)
  - Act of military surrender of the Wehrmacht signed at the Supreme Headquarters Allied Expeditionary Force by German Chief-of-Staff General Alfred Jodl, Reims, France, 1945 May 7 (Box Oversize folder)
  - Japanese Instrument of Surrender, written agreement ending the Pacific War and with it World War II. Signed by representatives from the Empire of Japan, the United States of America, the Republic of China, the United Kingdom, the Union of the Soviet Socialist Republics, and in the interests of the other United Nations at war with Japan, Potsdam, Germany, 1945 July 26 (Box Oversize folder)
- Photographs (Box 10 A/V 75086)
  - 7 photos of dedication ceremonies for memorials in Tripoli, 1958 (Folder A)
  - 4 photos of NATO conference, 1957 (Folder B)
  - 8 photos of the crew of the USS Savo Island, 1944-1945 (Folder C)
  - 11 photos of Italian Admiral Mindelli on visit to the USS Intrepid, 1955 (Folder D)
  - 2 photos of Mr. Thomas, First Lord of the Admiralty, 1955 (Folder E)
  - 10 photos of the commissioning of the USS Savo Island, 1944 (Folder F)
  - 7 photos of the ceremony commissioning the USS Kenneth Whiting, undated (Folder G)
  - 6 photos of Vice Admiral Ofstie, R.N., Rear Admiral Collet, R.N. and Captain Pedder, R.N., undated (Folder H)
  - 4 photos of a visit to the Mechanical Metallurgy Industry, Milan, 1956 (Folder I)
  - 66 photos of the USS Franklin D. Roosevelt, 1949-1950 (Folder J)
  - 11 photos of Guantanamo Bay, Cuba, 1927 (Folder K)
  - 8 photos reviewing the U.S. Marine Corps, San Diego, 1960 (Folder L)
  - 35 photos of the Sixth Fleet, change of Command, 1959 (Folder M)
  - 6 photos of the HMS Ark Royal, 1958 (Folder N)
  - 4 photos of J.J.L. Willinge, R.A., 1950 (Folder O)
  - 1 photo of Neil McElroy, Secretary of Defense, 1957-1960 (Folder P)
  - 5 photos of the First Marine Aircraft Wing, 1961 (Folder Q)
  - 2 photos of the dedication of the Naval Air Station Lemoore, undated (Folder R)
  - 2 photos of the inspection of the USS Oriskany, undated (Folder S)
  - 15 photos of Italian Admiral Atsugi's visit and Rear Admiral Sharp (Corn Fair West Pac), Oct. 1962 (Folder T)
  - 10 photos of US aircraft carriers and submarines, undated (Folder U)
  - 2 photos of Commander Fleet Air Eastern Atlantic/Mediterranean/Comnavactsoned and Staff, 1958 (Folder V)
  - 6 photos of Apollo Space Mission, 1962 (Folder W)
  - 148 photos and candid shots of Vice Admiral Clarence E. Ekstrom with officials, 1959-62 (Folder X-Z)
  - 5 photo albums relating to the USS Des Moines' visit to European ports and with foreign and U.S. dignitaries and officials, 1959 (Folder fAA-EE)
  - 1 photo album relating to a memorial reunion aboard the USS Bunker, 1970 (Folder fFF)
  - 1 album of 12 Elected Explorer Delegate Conference, 1961 (Folder fGG)
  - 1 album of the Gray Eagle Presentation, 1962 (Folder fHH)
  - 1 album of Admiral Halsey Field, 1961 (Folder fII)
  - 1 album of the visit of Secretary of the Navy (John B. Connally Jr.), 1962 (Folder fJJ)
  - 2 albums of the U.S. Navy, U.S. Marine Corps, U.S. First Fleet exercise, 1961 (Folder fKK)
  - 1 photo of Guantanamo Bay, 1927 (Folder mLL)
  - 4 photos of the USS Randolph, 1957 (Folder mMM)
  - 1 photo of the U.S. Naval Postgraduate School Class, 1930 (Folder mNN)
  - 2 photos of Commander Fleet Air Eastern Atlantic/Mediterranean Co. staff, 1957 (Folder mOO)
  - 2 color photo portraits of Vice Admiral Clarence E. Ekstrom, undated (Folder mPP)
  - 1 photo of Fred Korth, Secretary of the Navy, 1962 (Folder mQQ)
  - 9 photos of U.S. President Dwight D. Eisenhower, 1952-1960 (Folder mRR)
  - 1 photo of the USS Franklin Delano Roosevelt Marine Detachment, 1949 (Folder m*SS)